[Music]
okay uh so we started looking at uh TD
learning right we looked at
td0 yes so what does td0 do for
us
H great yeah but it does
essentially right it does evaluation
right it just gives given a policy
Pi it finds out what V Pi is right and
uses sample backup and
bootstrap
so how do we do
control
huh use the Q function in of the V
function that's
it
what we do is fix a policy pi and use
the Q function and learn the Q Pi for
the policy and
then fin
take ma Max of that and then you get a
new policy and then you go ahead with
the is okay so that's one way of doing
control with td0 right right so in fact
I can do that even if I have V but with
V finding a greedy policy is hard so
what I can do is I can take the Q
function right so can you do you want to
write down how this is going to look
like
here what goes in
here what goes in there
huh you think
so
to
uh okay so let's because I put RT + 1 we
have to add
the T everywhere sorry
there okay so instead of S D A Das I put
a t + 1 t St t + 1 a t + 1 okay so if
you stop and think about it what should
really go here
is right so if you remember this is
the that is the current
estimate
right that's a Target so this whole
thing gives you
a error right so did I mention TD error
in the last
class right so this expression that you
get in the TD Z update that expression
is called the TD error right what is the
TD error RT plus gamma v s v Old St + 1
minus V Old St that quantity is called
the TD error so I said it's some error
term so whatever error term you use in
the TD update it's called the TD error
and the error term you would use in the
monoral update is called the monoral
error blah blah whatever you want but TD
error is the more important thing okay
so sometimes we so the TD
error is special
enough to get its own
symbol right Delta so typically when I
say TD error Delta without any other
quantification it's the error on the V
function okay just just more of a
historic note so whever I use Delta I'll
Define what Delta is but typically Delta
by itself typic stands for the error on
the V function okay um good so ideally I
want this why because I'm using this as
my Target and what is my target it is
expected return starting from this point
right that is the target since I don't
have the expected return I'm using a
sample return which is what monlo gave
us I said instead of using a sample
return I'll use bootstrapping to correct
that return so I'll use the immediate
reward plus gamma * V right that gives
me the corrected return right so ideally
I should be using the return here but
why am I using the Q function
here
huh yeah so why am I using that just the
action I took
alone right I what should I what I
should have used there is expectation
over my
policy right people see this this is
essentially equal
[Music]
to
right whatever whatever is my current
policy that is expect so expected value
of Q comma St a +1 where a +1 is taken
according to the current policy right so
that is V but instead of computing this
expectation right I'm just taking one
sample from that
expectation that's basically what I'm
doing so if I apply this rule often
enough I will eventually compute this
expectation
the policy taking why not writing Pi
comma q q Pi comma old Q Pi under that
single policy we are taking this yeah I
mean if you're not updating the policy
doesn't matter
right and if you want to put the pi
here but since I fixed a policy I don't
I don't worry about it you should asked
me this question in V okay it makes more
sense but here the there's another
reason why I'm avoiding the pi I'll tell
you in a minute right so V if you want
use V Pi don't use V Pi that's fine
right so this is how we will estimate Q
right so you understand why we are
putting in this here now okay we putting
this here as
a estimate for this expectation right as
a unbiased estimate for this
expectation everyone with me okay
good so what do I do now I run a few
iterations of this learn the Q function
be greedy with respect to that Q
function and I can update my policy and
then run it again okay that is one way
of doing control okay there is another
way of doing
control well which is exactly the same
way what I told you except that instead
of running it for several iterations
with the same policy Pi you take one
step with that policy
Pi update the Q function and the next
time you have to choose an action be
greedy with respect to the current Q
function
function if you remember we talked about
this in generalized policy iteration
right you can just take one step and
then next time you can be greedy with
respect to just that one update you have
done right so you don't fix a policy in
this sense in this case in inste of
having a fixed policy every time you
have to pick an action you just look at
the Q function and pick the greedy
action so this is like running
extreme extreme generalized policy
iteration right so for every step you
just take one step with that policy for
the next time step you be greedy with
respect to the value function update
that you have done right you just keep
alternating between being greedy and
being and and updating the value
function right you just keep going back
and forth for one step update the value
function next time you be greedy right
so putting all of this together you can
actually get a algorithm like this so
you start off
with arbitrary Q
function
okay
then
right
okay so pick an action at to perform in
state St according to the current Q
value right so why do I put according to
the current Q
value you could just pick a greedy
action but we know from our Bandit
experience Being Greedy always is a bad
thing
so you need to do some kind of
exploration so you be greedy a lot okay
you explore
right so you can either do this
with some kind of
a Epsilon grey kind of an
approach right or you can
do soft Max or you can do anything
whatever whatever takes your fancy come
up with a good exploration strategy
right so people do basian exploration
and there are many many different ways
optimal ways in which to do this
exploration right uh great
now okay apply a and you sample St +1 RT
+1 right you could sample this if you
have a sample model you could just run
this through simulation or you could
just perform it in the real world and
get the St +1 rt+ 1 right now comes it
important
thing
pick
pick a + 1 according
to the Q
function okay the current Q
function okay now what you
do
is
I keep doing this until your episode
terminates right if once episode
terminates then you go back pick an S
not and keep doing this again and again
until
you you're happy with your Q
function okay okay fine everyone
agree so there is no explicit evaluation
stage there is no explicit greed
ification stage stage right so the
evaluation is done
here right and the greed ification is
done here right
here okay there are some small caveats
here so if you want this algorithm to
converge to something right what do you
think you should do
epon and then anything
else decrease Alpha also over time right
so decrease Alpha over time decrease
Epsilon over time so that eventually
you'll stop updating things but the
eventuality should happen a long long
long time into the
future right so you should explore a
lot right so that you have sampled every
state action PA often enough and your
Alpha shouldn't dek so quickly that even
while you are sampling it Alpha goes to
zero then there's no point in
sampling right so Alpha also should not
Decay till you have sampled enough okay
so both should Decay but should be
decaying at a slower Alpha should Decay
at a slower rate than
Epsilon okay is it good okay so this
is probably the second most popular
reinforcement learning algorithm that is
used for solving a lot of problems so
this is
called s anyone s
Sara so what what's
SSA sounds like a Mexican dish
or a dance
huh yeah yeah yeah yeah so it's a most
dumbest possible explanation for a
name okay State action reward next state
next action so you need the next action
also before you can perform these
updates therefore they called it
Sara hey the name stuck I
mean
and we have Rich Satan to blame for it I
mean he came up with the name not the
guys who originally proposed this
algorithm okay so they didn't come up
with this name guys called ramar and
nanjan um in fact uh couple of years ago
njan was going to come and spend like a
semester here on a on sabatical from
England but then last minute he changed
his mind so he never made it the guy who
proposed Sara I'm going to come and
spend a semester here but he didn't come
anyway so this is Sara
yeah this is an on policy
algorithm
why because I'm following this Epsilon
grey policy but I'm also updating the
value function corresponding to the
Epsilon grey
policy right because I'm using the
action that was actually taken right so
if you go back here this will be the
expected value according to Pi which
whatever Pi I'm following right so only
for that is this a sampler
correct right therefore this is on
policy algorithm okay in fact if you
stop and think about it for a second in
fact I can compute this expectation
without knowing anything about the
world no the expectation is only with
respect to p
and the quantity I'm taking the
expectation of is Q PI right I know both
Pi because that is as policy According
to which I'm taking
actions right and I
know the Q because that is a quantity
I'm estimating anyway so I might as well
compute this expectation explicitly I
don't have
to take a sample from for that
expectation in here in fact I can do the
exact computation so this
line I can replace with something like
this
explor that's why I said it is Computing
the Epsilon GD
Vol since you're updating for the
exploration steps as well it is actually
Computing the policy correspond value
function corresponding to the Epsilon
version Epsilon GD policy and that is
why I also called it on
policy right so you could do something
like
this right so in this case there are a
couple of interesting things here I
don't have to pick an action a priori
right so here we first picked the action
for a + 1 right and then we did the
updation and the way I have written the
loop you notice that I'm forcing you to
take this action here again the same
action you to I'm only saying apply 80
okay I'm not allowing you to pick again
right because if you pick again then you
are not on policy
anymore because I used a+1 to update
here if I allow you to pick another
action you are not on policy anymore
because my value function has changed
right I'll be picking a different action
Zone this is slightly subtle things
there right but here since I'm taking
the expectation it doesn't matter I can
go back and take a new action and I can
do this but this also makes
this
maybe kind of off policy sit somewhere
in the gray region between on policy and
off policy because I'm not actually
evaluating the action I
took right because at this
point I'm not trying to even build the
P
right so it's just how to think about it
a little bit right so at no point am I
having an explicit representation of a
pi anywhere in this s
algorithm there's no policy
here right it's implicitly defined by
the Q functions so when the Q function
changes the policy is automatically
changing right but here I'm explicitly
talking about a pi so I have to compute
this
P right and then I have to throw all of
this in and then I can become greedy
with Epsilon greedy with respect to the
new Q function I compute therefore the
pi also will change every step right so
apparently this has a name uh this is
called expected
sarsa okay frankly I never came across
this until the second edition of the
book and I had to go back and see if
there's actually a paper on this but
Rich also Cooks up things for the book
right all the off policy Monte Carlo
stuff that was there it never used to
exist before they wrote the first
edition of the book he just cooked it up
for the book okay so like that he might
have cooked up this expected soura for
the book I'm not sure
uh but uh he just likes to add
[Music]
[Applause]
things